<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D10'>
  <criteria primary='true' id='D10C1' title='Litter (excluding micro-litter)'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The composition, amount and spatial distribution of litter on the coastline, in
        the surface layer of the water column, and on the seabed, are at levels that do
        not cause harm to the coastal and marine environment.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for these levels through cooperation
        at Union level, taking into account regional or subregional specificities.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1"/>
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D10C2' title='Micro-litter'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The composition, amount and spatial distribution of micro-litter on the coastline,
        in the surface layer of the water column, and in seabed sediment, are at levels
        that do not cause harm to the coastal and marine environment.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for these levels through cooperation
        at Union level, taking into account regional or subregional specificities.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D10C3' title='Litter ingested'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The amount of litter and micro-litter ingested by marine animals is at a level
        that does not adversely affect the health of the species concerned.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for these levels through regional
        or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-3"/>
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D10C4' title='Adverse effects of litter'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The number of individuals of each species which are adversely affected due
        to litter, such as by entanglement, other types of injury or mortality, or
        health effects.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for the adverse effects of
        litter, through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-4"/>
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2"/>
  </criteria>

  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
      Subdivisions of the region or subregion, divided where needed by national
      boundaries.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
      The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be
      expressed for each criterion separately for each area assessed as follows:<br/>

      (a) the outcomes for each criterion (amount of litter or micro-litter per
      category) and its distribution per matrix used under D10C1 and D10C2 and
      whether the threshold values set have been achieved;<br/>

      (b) the outcomes for D10C3 (amount of litter and micro-litter per category
      per species) and whether the threshold values set have been achieved.<br/>

      The use of criteria D10C1, D10C2 and D10C3 in the overall assessment of good
      environmental status for Descriptor 10 shall be agreed at Union level.<br/>

      The outcomes of criterion D10C3 shall also contribute to assessments under
      Descriptor 1, where appropriate.<br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <methodological-standard id="m-2">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
      As used for assessment of the species group under Descriptor 1.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
      The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be
      expressed for each area assessed as follows:<br/>
      — for each species assessed under criterion D10C4, an estimate of the number
      of individuals in the assessment area that have been adversely affected.<br/>
      The use of criterion D10C4 in the overall assessment of good environmental
      status for Descriptor 10 shall be agreed at Union level.<br/>
      The outcomes of this criterion shall also contribute to assessments under
      Descriptor 1, where appropriate.<br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Litter (excluding micro-litter), classified in the following categories (13):
      artificial polymer materials, rubber, cloth/textile, paper/cardboard,
      processed/worked wood, metal, glass/ceramics, chemicals, undefined, and
      food waste.<br/>

      Member States may define further sub-categories.<br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-2">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Micro-litter (particles < 5mm), classified in the categories ‘artificial
      polymer materials’ and ‘other’.
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-3">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Litter and micro-litter classified in the categories ‘artificial polymer
      materials’ and ‘other’, assessed in any species from the following groups:
      birds, mammals, reptiles, fish or invertebrates.<br/>

      Member States shall establish that list of species to be assessed through
      regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-4">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Species of birds, mammals, reptiles, fish or invertebrates which are at risk
      from litter.<br/>

      Member States shall establish that list of species to be assessed through
      regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>
</descriptor-definition>
