<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D1'>
  <criteria primary='true' id='D1C1' title='Mortality rate from incidental by-catch'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The mortality rate per species from incidental by-catch is below
          levels which threaten the species, such that its long-term
          viability is ensured.<br/>
          Member States shall establish the threshold values for the mortality
          rate from incidental by-catch per species, through regional or
          subregional cooperation.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D1C2' title='Population abundance'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The population abundance of the species is not adversely affected due
          to anthropogenic pressures, such that its long-term viability is ensured. <br/>
          Member States shall establish threshold values for each species through regional
          or subregional cooperation, taking account of natural variation in population
          size and the mortality rates derived from D1C1, D8C4 and D10C4 and other relevant
          pressures. For species covered by Directive 92/43/EEC, these values shall be
          consistent with the Favourable Reference Population values established by the
          relevant Member States under Directive 92/43/EEC. <br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2"/>
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2"/>
  </criteria>

  <!-- D1C3 —
  Primary for commercially exploited fish(D1.4) and cephalopods(D1.5).
  Secondary for other species
  -->
  <criteria primary='raise error' id='D1C3' title='Population demographic characteristics'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The population demographic characteristics (e.g. body size or age class structure,
          sex ratio, fecundity, and survival rates) of the species are indicative of a healthy
          population which is not adversely affected due to anthropogenic pressures.<br/>

          Member States shall establish threshold values for specified characteristics of each
          species through regional or subregional cooperation, taking account of adverse effects
          on their health derived from D8C2, D8C4 and other relevant pressures.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2"/>
  </criteria>

  <!-- — Primary for species covered by
  Annexes II, IV or V to Directive 92/43/EEC
    - MAMMALS (D1.2)
    - REPTILES (D1.3)
    - FISH (D1.4)
  and secondary for other species
  -->
  <criteria primary='raise error' id='D1C4' title='Population distributional range and pattern'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The species distributional range and, where relevant, pattern is in line with prevailing
          physiographic, geographic and climatic conditions.<br/>
          Member States shall establish threshold values for each species through regional or
          subregional cooperation. For species covered by Directive 92/43/EEC, these shall be
          consistent with the Favourable Reference Range values established by the relevant Member
          States under Directive 92/43/EEC.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2"/>
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2"/>
  </criteria>

  <!-- — Primary for species covered by
  Annexes II, IV or V to Directive 92/43/EEC
    - MAMMALS (D1.2)
    - REPTILES (D1.3)
    - FISH (D1.4)
  and secondary for other species
  -->
  <criteria primary='raise error' id='D1C5' title='Habitat for the species'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The habitat for the species has the necessary extent and condition to support
          the different stages in the life history of the species.
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2"/>
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D1C6' title='Pelagic habitat condition'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The condition of the habitat type, including its biotic and abiotic structure and
          its functions (e.g. its typical species composition and their relative abundance,
          absence of particularly sensitive or fragile species or species providing a key
          function, size structure of species), is not adversely affected due to anthropogenic pressures.<br/>
          Member States shall establish threshold values for the condition of each habitat
          type, ensuring compatibility with related values set under Descriptors 2, 5 and 8,
          through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
            <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
            As used for assessment of the corresponding species or species groups under criteria D1C2-D1C5.
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
            The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed for each
            area assessed as follows:<br/>
            — the mortality rate per species and whether this has achieved the threshold value set.<br/>
            This criterion shall contribute to assessment of the corresponding species under criterion D1C2.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </methodological-standard>

  <methodological-standard id="m-2">
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
            <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
            As used for assessment of the corresponding species or species groups under criteria D1C2-D1C5.
        </p>
        <p>
            <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
            The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed for each area
            assessed as follows:<br/>
            — the mortality rate per species and whether this has achieved the threshold value set.<br/>
            This criterion shall contribute to assessment of the corresponding species under criterion D1C2.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
  </methodological-standard>


  <criteria-element id="el-1">
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          Species of birds, mammals, reptiles and non-commercially-exploited species of fish and cephalopods,
          which are at risk from incidental by-catch in the region or subregion.
          Member States shall establish that list of species through regional or subregional cooperation,
          pursuant to the obligations laid down in Article 25(5) of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013 for data
          collection activities and taking into account the list of species in Table 1D of the Annex to
          Commission Implementing Decision (EU) 2016/1251
        </p>
      ]]>
    </criteria-element>

    <criteria-element id="el-2">
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          Species groups, as listed under Table 1 and if present in the region or subregion.
          Member States shall establish a set of species representative of each species group, selected
          according to the criteria laid down under ‘specifications for the selection of species and habitats’,
          through regional or subregional cooperation. These shall include the mammals and reptiles listed in
          Annex II to Directive 92/43/EEC and may include any other species, such as those listed under Union
          legislation (other Annexes to Directive 92/43/EEC, Directive 2009/147/EC or through Regulation (EU)
          No 1380/2013) and international agreements such as Regional Sea Conventions.
        </p>
      ]]>
  </criteria-element>


  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
          <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
          Subdivision of region or subregion as used for assessments of benthic broad habitat
          types, reflecting biogeographic differences in species composition of the habitat
          type.
      </p>
      <p>
          <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
          The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed
          for each area assessed as:<br/>
          (a) an estimate of the proportion and extent of each habitat type assessed that
          has achieved the threshold value set;<br/>
          (b) a list of broad habitat types in the assessment area that were not assessed.
      </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Pelagic broad habitat types (variable salinity (17), coastal, shelf and oceanic/beyond
        shelf), if present in the region or subregion, and other habitat types as defined in
        the second paragraph.<br/>
        Member States may select, through regional or subregional cooperation, additional
        habitat types according to the criteria laid down under ‘specifications for the
        selection of species and habitats’.<br/>
     </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>
</descriptor-definition>
