<model xmlns:form="http://namespaces.plone.org/supermodel/form"
       xmlns:i18n="http://xml.zope.org/namespaces/i18n"
       xmlns:marshal="http://namespaces.plone.org/supermodel/marshal"
       xmlns:security="http://namespaces.plone.org/supermodel/security"
       xmlns="http://namespaces.plone.org/supermodel/schema">
    <schema>
        <field name="date_assessed"
               type="zope.schema.Text">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Date assessed</title>
        </field>
        <field name="authors"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Cover page authors</title>
            <default>Paola Banfi, Guillermo Gea, Lucille Labayle, David Landais, Melanie Muro, Goncalo Moreira,
            Alicia McNeil, and Imbory Thomas. The main authors are Richard White (D1, 4, 6),
            Elena San Martin (D2), Suzannah Walmsley (D3), William Parr (D5), Christophe Le Visage (D7),
            Norman Green (D8 and 9), Annemie Volckaert (D10) and Frank Thomsen (D11).</default>
        </field>
        <field name="contract"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Cover page contract</title>
            <default>No 11.0661/ENV/2018/791580/SER/ENV.C.2.</default>
        </field>
        <field name="logo"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Cover page logo</title>
            <default>
                &lt;img src="/++resource++static_images/cover_logos.png"&gt;
            </default>
        </field>
        <field name="scope_of_marine_waters"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Scope of marine waters</title>
        </field>
        <field name="length_of_coastline"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Length of coastline and area of marine waters</title>
        </field>
        <field name="assessment_methodology"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Assessment methodology</title>
            <default>
&lt;p&gt;The assessment applied the same broad criteria as the previous Article 12 assessment which was carried out between 2012 and 2014 to allow for an effective comparison and monitoring of progress:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha;"&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Adequacy: assessing whether the reported information is good enough to meet the objectives of the Directive and the technical requirements of Articles 8, 9 and 10. &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Consistency across the Marine Strategy (hereinafter: Consistency): assessing the logical flow of reporting of one Member State for Articles 8, 9 and 10, including the identification of missing links, conflicts, and gaps.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Regional coherence (hereinafter: Coherence): assessing the relationships between the reports of the Member States, within each marine region or subregion.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessment sought to identify progress in the implementation of the MSFD by comparing between 2012 and 2018 assessment results. A list of assessment questions by article for each of the three broad assessment criteria was defined to structure the assessment exercise. A scoring system is applied where each assessment question is scored based on the degree to which the broad assessment criteria are met by the reported information. The assessment is carried out through an online tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessment was based on the e-reporting information (xml and shapefiles) provided by the Member State. Any text reports submitted were not consulted.&lt;/p&gt;
            </default>
        </field>
        <field name="progress_recommendations_2012"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>2012 recommendations to Member State</title>
        </field>
        <field name="progress_recommendations_2018"
               type="plone.app.textfield.RichText">
            <description/>
            <required>False</required>
            <title>Progress against 2012 recommendations to Member State</title>
        </field>
    </schema>
</model>

