<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D6'>
  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C1'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Spatial extent and distribution of physical loss (permanent change) of the natural seabed.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C2'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Spatial extent and distribution of physical disturbance pressures on the seabed.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C3'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Spatial extent of each habitat type which is adversely affected, through change
        in its biotic and abiotic structure and its functions (e.g. through changes in
        species composition and their relative abundance, absence of particularly
        sensitive or fragile species or species providing a key function, size structure
        of species), by physical disturbance.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for the adverse effects of physical
        disturbance, through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-3" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>


  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C4'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The extent of loss of the habitat type, resulting from anthropogenic pressures,
        does not exceed a specified proportion of the natural extent of the habitat type
        in the assessment area.<br/>
        Member States shall establish the maximum allowable extent of habitat loss as a
        proportion of the total natural extent of the habitat type, through cooperation
        at Union level, taking into account regional or subregional specificities.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-4" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C5'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The extent of adverse effects from anthropogenic pressures on the condition of
        the habitat type, including alteration to its biotic and abiotic structure and
        its functions (e.g. its typical species composition and their relative abundance,
        absence of particularly sensitive or fragile species or species providing a key
        function, size structure of species), does not exceed a specified proportion of
        the natural extent of the habitat type in the assessment area.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for adverse effects on the
        condition of each habitat type, ensuring compatibility with related values set
        under Descriptors 2, 5, 6, 7 and 8, through cooperation at Union level, taking
        into account regional or subregional specificities.<br/>
        Member States shall establish the maximum allowable extent of those adverse
        effects as a proportion of the total natural extent of the habitat type, through
        cooperation at Union level, taking into account regional or subregional
        specificities.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-4" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2" />
  </criteria>


  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        As used for assessment of the benthic broad habitat types under Descriptors 1 and 6.
    <p>
        <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        The outcomes of assessment of criterion D6C1 (the distribution and an estimate of the
        extent of physical loss) shall be used to assess criteria D6C4 and D7C1.<br/>
        The outcomes of assessment of criterion D6C2 (the distribution and an estimate of the
        extent of physical disturbance pressures) shall be used to assess criterion D6C3.<br/>
        The outcomes of assessment of criterion D6C3 (an estimate of the extent of adverse 
        effect by physical disturbance per habitat type in each assessment area) shall 
        contribute to the assessment of criterion D6C5.<br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <methodological-standard id="m-2">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        Subdivision of region or subregion, reflecting biogeographic differences in species
        composition of the broad habitat type.
    <p>
        <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        A single assessment per habitat type, using criteria D6C4 and D6C5, shall serve the
        purpose of assessments of both benthic habitats under Descriptor 1 and sea-floor
        integrity under Descriptor 6.<br/>

        The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed
        for each area assessed as: <br/>

        (a) for D6C4, an estimate of the proportion and extent of loss per habitat type and
        whether this has achieved the extent value set; <br/>

        (b) for D6C5, an estimate of the proportion and extent of adverse effects, including
        the proportion lost from point (a), per habitat type and whether this has achieved
        the extent value set; <br/>

        (c) overall status of the habitat type, using a method agreed at Union level based
        on points (a) and (b), and a list of broad habitat types in the assessment area
        that were not assessed. <br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>


  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Physical loss of the seabed (including intertidal areas).
    /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-2">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Physical disturbance to the seabed (including intertidal areas).
    /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-3">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Benthic broad habitat types or other habitat types, as used under Descriptors 1 and 6.
    /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-4">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Benthic broad habitat types as listed in Table 2 and if present in the region or subregion,
      and other habitat types as defined in the second paragraph. <br/>

      Member States may select, through regional or subregional cooperation, additional habitat
      types, according to the criteria laid down under ‘specifications for the selection of species
      and habitats’, and which may include habitat types listed under Directive 92/43/EEC or
      international agreements such as Regional Sea Conventions, for the purposes of: <br/>

      (a) assessing each broad habitat type under criterion D6C5; <br/>

      (b) assessing these habitat types. <br/>

      A single set of habitat types shall serve the purpose of assessments of both benthic
      habitats under Descriptor 1 and sea-floor integrity under Descriptor 6. <br/>
    /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>
</descriptor-definition>
