<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D6'>
  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C1'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Spatial extent and distribution of physical loss (permanent change) of the natural seabed.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#mm-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C2'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Spatial extent and distribution of physical disturbance pressures on the seabed.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#mm-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C3'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Spatial extent of each habitat type which is adversely affected, through change
        in its biotic and abiotic structure and its functions (e.g. through changes in
        species composition and their relative abundance, absence of particularly
        sensitive or fragile species or species providing a key function, size structure
        of species), by physical disturbance.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for the adverse effects of physical
        disturbance, through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-3" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>


  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C4'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The extent of loss of the habitat type, resulting from anthropogenic pressures,
        does not exceed a specified proportion of the natural extent of the habitat type
        in the assessment area.<br/>
        Member States shall establish the maximum allowable extent of habitat loss as a
        proportion of the total natural extent of the habitat type, through cooperation
        at Union level, taking into account regional or subregional specificities.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-4" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D6C5'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The extent of loss of the habitat type, resulting from anthropogenic pressures,
        does not exceed a specified proportion of the natural extent of the habitat type
        in the assessment area.<br/>
        Member States shall establish the maximum allowable extent of habitat loss as a
        proportion of the total natural extent of the habitat type, through cooperation
        at Union level, taking into account regional or subregional specificities.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-4" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2" />
  </criteria>


  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        Subdivision of region or subregion as used for assessments of benthic broad habitat
        types, reflecting biogeographic differences in species composition of the habitat
        type.
    <p>
        <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed
        for each area assessed as:<br/>
        (a) an estimate of the proportion and extent of each habitat type assessed that
        has achieved the threshold value set;<br/>
        (b) a list of broad habitat types in the assessment area that were not assessed.
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Pelagic broad habitat types (variable salinity (17), coastal, shelf and oceanic/beyond
      shelf), if present in the region or subregion, and other habitat types as defined in
      the second paragraph.<br/>
      Member States may select, through regional or subregional cooperation, additional
      habitat types according to the criteria laid down under ‘specifications for the
      selection of species and habitats’.<br/>
    /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

</descriptor-definition>

<descriptor-definition id='D4'>
  <criteria primary='true' id='D4C1'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The diversity (species composition and their relative abundance) of the trophic guild is
        not adversely affected due to anthropogenic pressures.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values through regional or subregional
        cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D4C2'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The balance of total abundance between the trophic guilds is not adversely affected due to
        anthropogenic pressures.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D4C3'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The size distribution of individuals across the trophic guild is not adversely affected due to
        anthropogenic pressures.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D4C4'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Productivity of the trophic guild is not adversely affected due to anthropogenic pressures.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1"/>
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
  </criteria>

  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        Regional level for Baltic Sea and Black Sea; subregional level for North-East Atlantic and
        Mediterranean Sea.<br/>
        Subdivisions may be used where appropriate.
    <p>
        <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        Where values do not fall within the threshold values, this may trigger further research and
        investigation to understand the causes for the failure
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Trophic guilds of an ecosystem.<br/>
      Member States shall establish the list of trophic guilds through regional or subregional cooperation.
    /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

</descriptor-definition>