<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D11'>
  <criteria primary='true' id='D11C1' title='Introduction of energy, including
    underwater noise, is at levels that do not adversely affect the marine
    environment'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The spatial distribution, temporal extent, and levels of anthropogenic
          impulsive sound sources do not exceed levels that adversely affect 
          populations of marine animals.<br/>
          Member States shall establish threshold values for these levels through
          cooperation at Union level, taking into account regional or subregional
          specificities.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D11C2' title='Introduction of energy, including
    underwater noise, is at levels that do not adversely affect the marine
    environment'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The spatial distribution, temporal extent and levels of anthropogenic
          continuous low-frequency sound do not exceed levels that adversely
          affect populations of marine animals.<br/>
          Member States shall establish threshold values for these levels
          through cooperation at Union level, taking into account regional or
          subregional specificities.<br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
          <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
          Region, subregion or subdivisions.
      </p>    
      <p>
          <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
          The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be
          expressed for each area assessed as follows:<br/>
          (a)  for D11C1, the duration per calendar year of impulsive sound sources,
          their distribution within the year and spatially within the assessment area,
          and whether the threshold values set have been achieved;<br/>
          (b)  for D11C2, the annual average of the sound level, or other suitable
          temporal metric agreed at regional or subregional level, per unit area and
          its spatial distribution within the assessment area, and the extent (%, km2)
          of the assessment area over which the threshold values set have been achieved.<br/>

          The use of criteria D11C1 and D11C2 in the assessment of good environmental status
          for Descriptor 11 shall be agreed at Union level.<br/>
          The outcomes of these criteria shall also contribute to assessments under
          Descriptor 1.<br/>
      </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Anthropogenic impulsive sound in water.
      </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-2">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Anthropogenic continuous low-frequency sound in water.
      </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>
</descriptor-definition>
