<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D3'>

    <criteria primary='true' id='D3C1' title='Populations of all commercially-exploited
     fish and shellfish are within safe biological limits, exhibiting a population age
     and size distribution that is indicative of a healthy stock'>
      <definition>
        <![CDATA[
          <p>
            The Fishing mortality rate of populations of commercially-exploited 
            species is at or below levels which can produce the maximum sustainable 
            yield (MSY). Appropriate scientific bodies shall be consulted in accordance 
            with Article 26 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013.
          </p>
        ]]>      
      </definition>
      <uses-element href="#el-1"/>
      <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
    </criteria>

    <criteria primary='true' id='D3C2' title='Populations of all commercially-exploited
     fish and shellfish are within safe biological limits, exhibiting a population age
     and size distribution that is indicative of a healthy stock'>
      <definition> 
        <![CDATA[
          <p>
            The Spawning Stock Biomass of populations of commercially-exploited species 
            are above biomass levels capable of producing maximum sustainable yield. 
            Appropriate scientific bodies shall be consulted in accordance with Article 26 
            of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013.
          </p>
        ]]>      
      </definition>
      <uses-element href="#el-1"/>
      <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
    </criteria>
    
    <criteria primary='true' id='D3C3' title='Populations of all commercially-exploited
     fish and shellfish are within safe biological limits, exhibiting a population age
     and size distribution that is indicative of a healthy stock'>
      <definition>
        <![CDATA[
          <p>
            The age and size distribution of individuals in the populations of 
            commercially-exploited species is indicative of a healthy population. 
            This shall include a high proportion of old/large individuals and limited 
            adverse effects of exploitation on genetic diversity. <br/>
            Member States shall establish threshold values through regional or subregional
            cooperation for each population of species in accordance with scientific advice 
            obtained pursuant to Article 26 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013.
          </p>
        ]]>      
      </definition>
      <uses-element href="#el-1"/>
      <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
    </criteria>

    <methodological-standard id="m1">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>
            <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
            Populations of each species are assessed at ecologically-relevant scales within
            each region or subregion, as established by appropriate scientific bodies 
            as referred to in Article 26 of Regulation (EU) No 1380/2013, based on specified
            aggregations of International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES) areas,
            General Fisheries Commission for the Mediterranean (GFCM) geographical sub-areas 
            and Food and Agriculture Organisation (FAO) fishing areas for the Macaronesian 
            biogeographic region.
          </p>

          <p>
            <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
            The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be 
            expressed for each area assessed as follows: <br/>
            (a) the populations assessed, the values achieved for each criterion and
            whether the levels for D3C1 and D3C2 and the threshold values for D3C3 
            have been achieved, and the overall status of the population on the basis
            of criteria integration rules agreed at Union level; <br/>
            (b) the populations of commercially-exploited species in the assessment 
            area which were not assessed. <br/>
            The outcomes of these population assessments shall also contribute to
            the assessments under Descriptors 1 and 6, if the species are relevant
            for assessment of particular species groups and benthic habitat types.<br/>
          </p>
        ]]>
    </methodological-standard>


  <criteria-element id="el-1">
        <![CDATA[
          <p>
              Commercially-exploited fish and shellfish.<br/>
              Member States shall establish through regional or subregional cooperation
              a list of commercially-exploited fish and shellfish, according to the criteria
              laid down under ‘specifications’
          </p>
        ]]>
  </criteria-element>
</descriptor-definition>