<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D5'>
    <criteria primary='true' id='D5C1'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Nutrient concentrations are not at levels that indicate adverse
        eutrophication effects.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D5C2'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Chlorophyll a concentrations are not at levels that indicate adverse
        effects of nutrient enrichment
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D5C3'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The number, spatial extent and duration of harmful algal bloom events
        are not at levels that indicate adverse effects of nutrient
        enrichment.<br/>
        Member States shall establish threshold values for these levels through
        regional or subregional cooperation.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-3" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D5C4'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The photic limit (transparency) of the water column is not reduced, due
        to increases in suspended algae, to a level that indicates adverse
        effects of nutrient enrichment.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-4" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D5C5'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The concentration of dissolved oxygen is not reduced, due to nutrient
        enrichment, to levels that indicate adverse effects on benthic habitats
        (including on associated biota and mobile species) or other eutrophication
        effects.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-5" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D5C6'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The abundance of opportunistic macroalgae is not at levels that indicate
        adverse effects of nutrient enrichment.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-6" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D5C7'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The species composition and relative abundance or depth distribution of
        macrophyte communities achieve values that indicate there is no adverse
        effect due to nutrient enrichment including via a decrease in water
        transparency
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-7" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D5C8'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The species composition and relative abundance of macrofaunal communities,
        achieve values that indicate that there is no adverse effect due to nutrient
        and organic enrichment
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-8" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        - within coastal waters, as used under Directive 2000/60/EC, <br/>
        - beyond coastal waters, subdivisions of the region or subregion,
        divided where needed by national boundaries.
    </p>

    <p>
      <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed for each area assessed as follows:
        (a) the values achieved for each criterion used, and an estimate of the extent of the assessment area over which the threshold values set have been achieved; <br/>
        (b) in coastal waters, the criteria shall be used in accordance with the requirements of Directive 2000/60/EC to conclude on whether the water body is subject to eutrophication (5); <br/>
        (c) beyond coastal waters, an estimate of the extent of the area (as a proportion (percentage)) that is not subject to eutrophication (as indicated by the results of all criteria used, integrated in a manner agreed where possible at Union level, but at least at regional or subregional level). <br/>

        Beyond coastal waters, the use of the secondary criteria shall be agreed at regional or subregional level. <br/>

        The outcomes of the assessments shall also contribute to assessments for pelagic habitats under Descriptor 1 as follows: <br/>
        - the distribution and an estimate of the extent of the area (as a proportion (percentage)) that is subject to eutrophication in the water column (as indicated by whether the threshold values for criteria D5C2, D5C3 and D5C4, when used, have been achieved); <br/>

        The outcomes of the assessments shall also contribute to assessments for benthic habitats under Descriptors 1 and 6 as follows: <br/>
        - the distribution and an estimate of the extent of the area (as a proportion (percentage)) that is subject to eutrophication on theseabed (as indicated by whether the threshold values for criteria D5C4, D5C5, D5C6, D5C7 and D5C8, when used, have been achieved).
    </p>

    <p>
        <strong>Threshold values:</strong><br/>
        (a) in coastal waters, the values set in accordance with Directive 2000/60/EC; <br/>
        (b) should this criterion be relevant for waters beyond coastal waters, values
        consistent with those for coastal waters under Directive 2000/60/EC. Member States shall establish those values through regional or subregional cooperation. </br>
    </p>

    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        Nutrients in the water column: <br/>
        Dissolved Inorganic Nitrogen (DIN), Total Nitrogen (TN), Dissolved Inorganic Phosphorus (DIP), Total Phosphorus (TP).
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-2">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Chlorophyll a in the water column
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-3">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Harmful algal blooms (e.g. cyanobacteria) in the water column
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-4">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Photic limit (transparency) of the water column
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-5">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        Photic limit (transparency) of the water column
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-5">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        Dissolved oxygen in the bottom of the water column
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-6">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        Opportunistic macroalgae of benthic habitats
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-7">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        Macrophyte communities (perennial seaweeds and seagrasses
        such as fucoids, eelgrass and Neptune grass) of benthic habitats
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-8">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        Macrofaunal communities of benthic habitats
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

</descriptor-definition>
