<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D7'>
    <criteria primary='false' id='D7C1'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          Spatial extent and distribution of permanent alteration of hydrographical conditions
          (e.g. changes in wave action, currents, salinity, temperature) to the seabed and
          water column, associated in particular with physical loss of the natural seabed.
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>
    
  <criteria primary='false' id='D7C2'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          Spatial extent of each benthic habitat type adversely affected (physical and
          hydrographical characteristics and associated biological communities) due to
          permanent alteration of hydrographical conditions. <br/>
          Member States shall establish threshold values for the adverse effects of
          permanent alterations of hydrographical conditions, through regional or
          subregional cooperation. <br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        As used for assessment of the benthic broad habitat types under Descriptors 1 and 6.
      </p>

      <p>
        <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        The outcomes of assessment of criterion D7C1 (the distribution and an estimate of the
        extent of hydrographical changes) shall be used to assess criterion D7C2.<br/>
        The outcomes of assessment of criterion D7C2 (an estimate of the extent of
        adverse effect per habitat type in each assessment area) shall contribute to the assessment of criterion D6C5<br/>
      </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>
  
  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Hydrographical changes to the seabed and water column (including intertidal areas).
      /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-2">
    <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Benthic broad habitats types or other habitat types, as used for Descriptors 1 and 6.
      </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>
</descriptor-definition>