<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D8'>
    <criteria primary='true' id='D8C1'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        Within coastal and territorial waters, the concentrations of contaminants
        do not exceed the following threshold values: <br/>

        (a) for contaminants set out under point 1(a) of criteria elements,
        the values set in accordance with Directive 2000/60/EC; <br/>

        (b) when contaminants under point (a) are measured in a matrix for which
        no value is set under Directive 2000/60/EC, the concentration of those
        contaminants in that matrix established by Member States through regional or subregional cooperation; <br/>

        (c) for additional contaminants selected under point 1(b) of criteria elements,
        the concentrations for a specified matrix (water, sediment or biota) which may
        give rise to pollution effects. Member States shall establish these concentrations through regional or subregional cooperation, considering their application within and beyond coastal and territorial waters. <br/>

        Beyond territorial waters, the concentrations of contaminants do not exceed the
        following threshold values: <br/>
        (a) for contaminants selected under point 2(a) of criteria elements, the values
        as applicable within coastal and territorial waters; <br/>

        (b) for contaminants selected under point 2(b) of criteria elements, the concentrations
        for a specified matrix (water, sediment or biota) which may give rise to pollution effects. 
        Member States shall establish these concentrations through regional or subregional cooperation. <br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>
    
  <criteria primary='false' id='D8C2'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The health of species and the condition of habitats (such as their species composition
        and relative abundance at locations of chronic pollution) are not adversely affected due
        to contaminants including cumulative and synergetic effects.<br/>
        Member States shall establish those adverse effects and their threshold values through
        regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-2" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='true' id='D8C3'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The spatial extent and duration of significant acute pollution events are minimised.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-3" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-2" />
  </criteria>

  <criteria primary='false' id='D8C4'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
      <p>
        The adverse effects of significant acute pollution events on the health of species
        and on the condition of habitats (such as their species composition and relative
        abundance) are minimised and, where possible, eliminated.
      </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-4" />
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-3" />
  </criteria>


  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        — within coastal and territorial waters, as used under Directive 2000/60/EC,<br/>

        — beyond territorial waters, subdivisions of the region or subregion, divided
        where needed by national boundaries.<br/>
    </p>

    <p>
      <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
      The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed
      for each area assessed as follows:

      (a) for each contaminant under criterion D8C1, its concentration, the matrix used
      (water, sediment, biota), whether the threshold values set have been achieved, and
      the proportion of contaminants assessed which have achieved the threshold values,
      including indicating separately substances behaving like ubiquitous persistent,
      bioaccumulative and toxic substances (uPBTs), as referred to in Article 8a(1)(a)
      of Directive 2008/105/EC; <br/>

      (b) for each species assessed under criterion D8C2, an estimate of the abundance of
      its population in the assessment area that is adversely affected; <br/>

      (c) for each habitat assessed under criterion D8C2, an estimate of the extent in the
      assessment area that is adversely affected. <br/>

      The use of criterion D8C2 in the overall assessment of good environmental status for
      Descriptor 8 shall be agreed at regional or subregional level. <br/>

      The outcomes of the assessment of criterion D8C2 shall contribute to assessments under
      Descriptors 1 and 6, where appropriate <br/>

      </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>
  
  <methodological-standard id="m-2">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        Regional or subregional level, divided where needed by national boundaries.
    </p>

    <p>
        <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed
        for each area assessed as follows: <br/>
        — an estimate of the total spatial extent of significant acute pollution events and
        their distribution and total duration for each year. <br/>
        This criterion shall be used to trigger assessment of criterion D8C4.
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <methodological-standard id="m-3">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
        <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
        Regional or subregional level, divided where needed by national boundaries.
    </p>

    <p>
        <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
        The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed for each area assessed as follows: <br/>
        — an estimate of the total spatial extent of significant acute pollution events and their distribution and total duration for each year. <br/>
        This criterion shall be used to trigger assessment of criterion D8C4. <br/>
    </p>
    ]]>
  </methodological-standard>


  <criteria-element id="el-1">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Within coastal and territorial waters:<br/>

      (a) contaminants selected in accordance with Directive 2000/60/EC:<br/>
      (i) contaminants for which an environmental quality standard is laid down in Part A
      of Annex I to Directive 2008/105/EC;<br/>
      (ii) River Basin Specific Pollutants under Annex VIII to Directive 2000/60/EC, in
      coastal waters;<br/>

      (b) additional contaminants, if relevant, such as from offshore sources, which are
      not already identified under point (a) and which may give rise to pollution effects
      in the region or subregion. Member States shall establish that list of contaminants
      through regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>

      (2) Beyond territorial waters:<br/>
      (a) the contaminants considered under point (1), where these still may give rise to
      pollution effects;<br/>

      (b) additional contaminants, if relevant, which are not already identified under point
      (2)(a) and which may give rise to pollution effects in the region or subregion. Member
      States shall establish that list of contaminants through regional or subregional
      cooperation.<br/>

    /p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-2">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Species and habitats which are at risk from contaminants.<br/>
      Member States shall establish that list of species, and
      relevant tissues to be assessed, and habitats, through
      regional or subregional cooperation.
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-3">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Significant acute pollution events involving polluting substances, as defined in Article 2(2)
      of Directive 2005/35/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council, including crude oil and
      similar compounds.
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

  <criteria-element id="el-4">
    <![CDATA[
    <p>
      Species of the species groups, as listed under Table 1 of Part II, and benthic broad habitat types,
      as listed under Table 2 of Part II.
    </p>
    ]]>
  </criteria-element>

</descriptor-definition>