<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<descriptor-definition id='D9'>
    <criteria primary='true' id='D9C1'>
    <definition>
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          The level of contaminants in edible tissues (muscle, liver, roe, flesh or other soft
          parts, as appropriate) of seafood (including fish, crustaceans, molluscs, echinoderms,
          seaweed and other marine plants) caught or harvested in the wild (excluding fin-fish
          from mariculture) does not exceed: <br/>

          (a) for contaminants listed in Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006, the maximum levels laid
          down in that Regulation, which are the threshold values for the purposes of this Decision; <br/>

          (b) for additional contaminants, not listed in Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006, threshold values,
          which Member States shall establish through regional or subregional cooperation <br/>
        </p>
      ]]>
    </definition>
    <uses-element href="#el-1"/>
    <uses-methodological-standard href="#m-1"/>
  </criteria>

  <methodological-standard id="m-1">
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          <strong>Scale of assessment:</strong><br/>
          The catch or production area in accordance with Article 38 of Regulation (EU)
          No 1379/2013 of the European Parliament and of the Council.
        <p>
          <strong>Use of criteria: </strong><br/>
          The extent to which good environmental status has been achieved shall be expressed
          for each area assessed as follows: <br/>
          — for each contaminant, its concentration in seafood, the matrix used (species and
          tissue), whether the threshold values set have been achieved, and the proportion of
          contaminants assessed which have achieved their threshold values.
        </p>
      ]]>
  </methodological-standard>

  <criteria-element id="el-1">
      <![CDATA[
        <p>
          Contaminants listed in Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006.<br/>

          For the purposes of this Decision, Member States may decide not to consider contaminants
          from Regulation (EC) No 1881/2006 where justified on the basis of a risk assessment.<br/>

          Member States may assess additional contaminants that are not included in Regulation (EC)
          No 1881/2006. Member States shall establish a list of those additional contaminants throgh
          regional or subregional cooperation.<br/>

          Member States shall establish the list of species and relevant tissues to be assessed,
          according to the conditions laid down under ‘specifications’. They may cooperate at regional
          or subregional level to establish that list of species and relevant tissues.<br/>
        /p>
      ]]>
  </criteria-element>
</descriptor-definition>